# Yoonsu Kim

Ph.D. Student | HCI Researcher

☑ yoonsu16@kaist.ac.kr | kysoo816@gmail.com 🏠 https://yoonsu0816.github.io/

## **Research Interests**

My research interests include around **Human-Computer Interaction**, **Human-Centered AI**, and **Human-AI** collaboration.

I am passionate about developing new interactions and systems that help people better utilize AI technology and understand the difficulties in using it or trying to use it.

#### Education

**KAIST** 

Ph.D. in School of Computing

Advisor: <u>Juho Kim</u>

**KAIST** 

M.S. in AI (Specialization: Human-AI Interaction)

Advisor: Juho Kim

**POSTECH** 

B.S. in Computer Science and Engineering

Magna cum laude

Feb 2024 - Present

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

Feb 2022 - Feb 2024

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

Feb 2017 - Feb 2022

Pohang, Republic of Korea

### **Publications**

## Conference and Journal Papers

[C1] Understanding Users' Dissatisfaction with ChatGPT Responses: Types, Resolving Tactics, and the Effect of Knowledge Level

**Yoonsu Kim**, Jueon Lee, Seoyoung Kim, Jaehyuk Park, Juho Kim *ACM Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI 2024) (to appear)* 

[C2] AI-to-Human Actuation: AI Proactively Induces Humans towards Favorable Sensing Conditions

Sungjae Cho, **Yoonsu Kim**, Jaewoong Jang, Inseok Hwang *Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT 2023)*.

## Posters, Demos, Workshop Papers

[D1] RECIPE: How to Integrate ChatGPT into EFL Writing Education

Sungjae Cho, Yoonsu Kim, Jaewoong Jang, Inseok Hwang

Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT 2023).

Last updated: Jan 20, 2024

[D2] Towards Understanding the Challenges and Remedies in AI Application Development
Dae Hyun Kim\*, Yoonsu Kim\*, Hyungyu Shin, Jinho Son, Juho Kim (\* Corresponding authors)
Korea Computer Congress 2023 (KCC 2023)

# [D3] Demonstrating AHA: Boosting Unmodified AI's Robustness by Proactively Inducing Favorable Human Sensing Conditions

Sungjae Cho, Jaewoong Jang, **Yoonsu Kim**, Inseok Hwang Adjunct Proceedings of the 2023 ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing & the 2023 ACM International Symposium on Wearable Computing (UbiComp/ISWC '23 Adjunct)

# **Experiences**

HIS Lab (Human-Centered Intelligent System Lab in POSTECH)

Research Intern

Jun 2021 - Feb 2022

Human-Computer Interaction, Human-AI Interaction, Embedded AI System

Pohang, Republic of Korea

**NAVER Connect Foundation** 

Manager of boostcamp

While A Marin and Company Seoul, Republic of Korea

Web & Mobile, AI Software Education

Neuromeka
Software Development Intern
Jun 2019 - Aug 2019

Android application development for robot manipulation

Pohang, Republic of Korea

Samsung Electronics Co.

and robot database management

Research Intern

Suwon, Republic of Korea

Department of Visual Display, AI • Big Data Lab

SK Telecom

Software Development Intern

Department of Service Platform

Jun 2018 - Aug 2018

Seoul, Republic of Korea

AI Technology Unit, Knowledge and Technology Cell

# Scholarship

National Scholarship (Science and Engineering) 2017 - 2023

Global Leadership Program Mar 2018 - Feb 2020

Samsung Dream Class Scholarship Jan. 2018 ~ Feb. 2018

# Leadership & Service

Director of Welfare department

### Leadership

KAIST-Google exploreCSR
Mar 2023 - Present

Student Organizer

POSTECH Student Council Feb 2019 - Feb 2021

Last updated: Jan 20, 2024

#### **POSTECH Library Council**

President, Vice President Mar 2017 - Aug 2019

#### **POSTECH Reader's Club 6**

(Awarded by Excellent Mentee) Feb 2019 - Dec 2018

**POSTECH Reader's Club 5** 

# Teaching

**POSTECH Programming and Problem Solving (CSED101)** 

Teaching Mentor Feb 2021 - Dec 2021

# Volunteering

KOICA WFK Korean Medicine Volunteer Group Overseas Medical Dec 2023

**Volunteer Activities**Krong Battambang,
Cambodia

KOICA WFK Korean Medicine Volunteer Group Overseas Medical Aug 2019

Volunteer Activities Toshken, Uzbekistan